<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE transcription SYSTEM "http://www.livesandletters.ac.uk/schema/aor_20141023.dtd">

<transcription xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
    xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://www.livesandletters.ac.uk/schema/aor2_18112016.xsd">
    <page filename="c_120_b_4_(2)_f039br.tif" reader="John Dee" status="fixed" origin="added"/> 
    <annotation>
        
        <marginalia hand="Italian">
            <language ident="LA">
                <position place="full_page" book_orientation="0">
                    <marginalia_text>
                        Eorum enim abscondita apparitio nequa[m]q[ue] significatur, nisi co[m]ponatur
                        eo quod no[n] perficimitur donec sui colores peragantur.
                    </marginalia_text>
                </position>
            </language>
            <translation>
                For the concealed attendance of these is by no means shown, unless constructed,
                because they are not accomplished as long as its colours are being disturbed.
            </translation>
        </marginalia>
        
        <marginalia hand="Italian">
            <language ident="LA">
                <position place="full_page" book_orientation="0">
                    <marginalia_text>
                        Et quod Elementu[m] sit minimu[m] Corporu[m] apparentium, patet per
                        eius definitione[m], Elementum enim minima particula corporis est.
                        Tertio videamus qualiter operetur natura. Et certe quatuor
                        modis, s[cilicet] secundum quatuor motus, qui sunt corruptio, generatio, 
                        Argumentum &amp; diminutio. Alteratio enim, est secundum 
                        qualitate[m] mutatio. Agit ergo Natura corrumpendo sed quia
                        Corruptionis multa[e] sunt species, tentemus solum de vna, qua[e]
                        vertutur in propositum n[ost]r[u[m]. Et certa vna est putrefactio.
                        Vnde Hermes in Allegoria sua, scitote, quod artis origo 
                        est caput corvi et vt sequitur.
                    </marginalia_text>
                    <person name="Hermes Trismegistus"/>
                </position>
            </language>
            <translation>
                And because the element is minimal in its evident bodies, it is evident through its definition, for the element is its smallest physical particles.
                Thirdly, we might see in what ways nature is worked. And certainly, in four modes, of course, according to its four motions, which are cossuption, generation, augmentation and diminuation.
                For an alteration are according to its quality a change. Therefore, nature acts by corrupting. 
                But because there are many types of changes, we <!-- tentemus solum de vna, quae vertitur in propositum m[???]m--> <!--JG: I think it's n[ost]r[u[m]-->
                And certainly, the one is putrefaction. From Hermes in his Allegoria, understand that the origin of the art is the head of a raven and what follows.
            </translation>
        </marginalia>
        
    </annotation>
</transcription>