<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE transcription SYSTEM "http://www.livesandletters.ac.uk/schema/aor_20141023.dtd">

<transcription xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
    xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://www.livesandletters.ac.uk/schema/aor_20141118.xsd">
    
    <page filename="00000867.tif" reader="Harvey"/>
    <annotation>
        
        <marginalia hand="Italian">
            <language ident="LA">
                <position place="tail" book_orientation="0">
                    <marginalia_text> 
                        Glarean&igrave;, et Velcurionis schola[e] Liuiana[e]: saltem post singulorum librorum lectionem, sigillatim percurrenda[e]: ne quid 
                        fort&egrave; pra[e]termittatur, pra[e]cipua observatione dignum. H&icirc;c enim qua[e]dam pra[e]gnantia, et exquisita: pla[e]raq[ue] 
                        alicuius nota[e]. Velcur&igrave;o fer&egrave; talis Politicus, pra[e]sertim in Catalogus Legum, atq[ue] Morum; qualis Italic&egrave;
                        Machiauellus in suis Liuianis Obseruationibus; inscriptis, Discorsi sopra la prima deca di T. Liuio. In vtroq[ue] egregia fundamenta 
                        tam Disciplina[e], qu&agrave;m Jurisprudentia[e] Romana[e]: nec quicq[uam] ferm&egrave;, aut industrio viro dignius, aut politico: 
                        pra[e]sertim post Aristotelis Principia Politica; vnd&egrave; omnes egregiae Hypotheses politica[e], in quovis Regnorum, aut 
                        Rerumpublicarum statu. Prudentis interest, ea perit&egrave;, profundeq[ue] seligere, qua[e] sunt suo Statui aptissima; nec tam 
                        acutissimum philosophum agere, qu&agrave;m reuer&acirc; vtilissimum politicum. Id et olim ciuis Romani erat; et hodi&egrave; est 
                        subiecti Britannici. Nihil excellens pra[e]termittendum: sed pra[e]cipu&egrave; Legum, Armorumq[ue] Mnemosyna, curioso, solidoq[ue] 
                        iudicio obseruanda: et siquid posset nostra[e] Reipublica[e] conducere, id est in primis perpendendum.
                    </marginalia_text>
                    <person name="Livy"/>
                    <person name="Heinrich Glarean"/>
                    <person name="Johannes Velcurio"/>
                    <person name="Machiavelli"/>
                    <person name="Aristotle"/>
                    <book title="Explicationes In T. Liuii Patavini"/>
                    <book title="In omneis Titi Livii decadas annotationes"/>
                    <book title="Discourses on Livy"/>
                    <book title="Politics"/>
                </position>
            </language>
            <translation>
                The Livian expositions of Glareanus and Velcurio should be skimmed one by one, at least after reading each one of the individual books, in case
                one accidentally missed out on something worthy particular notice. For some things here are rich in meaning and precise; and most are of at 
                least some significance. Velcurio was just such a politician, especially in his catalogue of laws and customs, as Macchiavelli was in his 
                commentary on Livy, entitled 'Discorsi sopra la prima deca di T. Livio'. In each of these one finds outstanding foundations of both Roman 
                discipline and jurisprudence; and hardly anything is more worthwhile for an active man, or politician, especially after Aristotle's Political 
                Principles. On these are based all excellent political Case studies of any form of kingdoms or republics. It is important for the prudent man 
                to choose expertly and meticulously which ones are most suitable for his form, and to act not so much as a very sharp philosopher but in fact 
                rather as an extremely useful politician. This was once also important for the Roman citizen, and it is today for the British subject. One must
                not skip any superb matter, but observe especially with a careful and firm judgment the track records of laws and military actions. And 
                anything that could be beneficial for our state should be examined above all.
            </translation>
        </marginalia>
        
        <marginalia hand="Italian" date="1580">
            <language ident="LA">
                <position place="tail" book_orientation="0">
                    <marginalia_text> 
                        gabriel harveius. 1580.
                    </marginalia_text>
                <person name="Gabriel Harvey"/>
                </position>
            </language>
            <translation>
                Gabriel Harvey, 1580.
            </translation>
        </marginalia>
        
        <marginalia hand="Italian">
            <language ident="LA">
                <position place="tail" book_orientation="0">
                    <marginalia_text> 
                        Tr&igrave;a Opt&igrave;ma Max&igrave;ma Romanorum biblia, Plinius, Liuius, Plutarchus: Plinius ad cognitionem: Liuius ad actionem: 
                        Plutarchus ad Vtramq[ue]. Summa summarum, Ca[e]sar: tam prudentissimi consilij, qu&agrave;m fortissima[e] actionis Auctor singularis; 
                        et omnino excellentissimus magister militaris Artis, et Virtut&igrave;s, id est, Victoria[e], ipsiusq[ue] Fortuna[e]. Politici interest,
                        Ca[e]sari adiungere Tacitum: qui perinde est Pragmaticorum solertissimus, vt Ca[e]sar bellatorum val&igrave;dissimus: vterq[ue] 
                        pernecessarius tam profundo consiliario, qu&agrave;m strenuo Duc&igrave;. Adde Heroica[e] Virtutis, diuiniq[ue] Zeli miracula: nihil 
                        supra.
                    </marginalia_text>
                <person name="Pliny the Elder"/>
                <person name="Livy"/>
                <person name="Plutarch"/>
                <person name="Julius Caesar"/>
                <person name="Tacitus"/>
                </position>
            </language>
            <translation>
                The three most superior books of the Romans are: Pliny, Livy, and Plutarch. Pliny for knowledge, Livy for action, Plutarch for both. Caesar is 
                the ultimate top: an extraordinary author of equally the most prudent counsel and the bravest action, as well as an absolutely superior master
                of military skill and virtue, in other words: of victory and fortune itself. It is useful for the politician to add Tacitus to Caesar, who is 
                the most expert of pragmatics in the same manner as Caesar is the most powerful of warriors. Both are absolutely essential for a thorough 
                counsellor as well as an energetic leader. Add to this the miracles of heroic virtue and divine zeal: there is nothing superior to that.
            </translation>
        </marginalia>
        
        <marginalia hand="Italian">
            <language ident="LA">
                <position place="tail" book_orientation="0">
                    <marginalia_text> 
                        Nullus historicorum tantum habet ciuilis iurisconsulti, aut forensis pragmatici, qu&agrave;m Liuius, et post eum Tacitus, callidusq[ue]
                        Frontinus. Nouissim&egrave; etiam Guicciardinus, Zuingerus, Chytraeus, alij perpauci nonnihil habent pragmatici. Hodi&egrave; multi 
                        asini ausi sunt componere historias, chronica, annales, commentarios: vt fer&egrave; Graftonus, Stous, Holinshedus, non pauci tales: 
                        nec iureconsulti, nec politici, nec ethologi, nec vllo modo eruditi. Liuium Britannicum qu&agrave;m diu desiderabimus? Ah quando 
                        exstabit Tacitus, Frontinusue Britannicus? Nugis affluimus: pragmaticaru[m], bellicarumue rerum qu&agrave;m ieiuna memoria? 
                        Solus fer&egrave; Morus, et Aschamus nonnihil attigerunt pristina[e] artis, et industria[e]. Tandem etiam Cambdenus, Hacluitus, [....]
                    </marginalia_text>
                    <person name="Livy"/>
                    <person name="Tacitus"/>
                    <person name="Frontinus"/>
                    <person name="Francesco Guicciardini"/>
                    <person name="Theodor Zwinger"/>
                    <person name="David Chytraeus"/> 
                    <person name="Richard Grafton"/> 
                    <person name="John Stow"/> 
                    <person name="Raphael Holinshed"/> 
                    <person name="Thomas More"/>
                    <person name="Roger Ascham"/>
                    <person name="William Camden"/> 
                    <person name="Richard Hakluyt"/> 
                </position>
            </language>
            <translation>
                No historian has so much of the civil lawyer or legal practitioner, as Livy, and after him, Tacitus and the shrewd Frontinus. Since very 
                recently also Guicciardini, Zwinger, Chytraeus, and very few others have some features of the pragmatic. Nowadays many asses have dared to 
                write histories, chronicles, annals and commentaries, such as Grafton, Stous, Holinshed, and not a few others of this kind. They are neither 
                jurists, nor politicians, nor experts in character, nor learned in any way whatsoever. How long will we be missing a British Livy? Ah, when 
                will there be a British Tacitus or Frontinus? We abound in worthless works, but how poor is our record of pragmatic and military affairs! Only
                More, almost, and Ascham took up some amount of the old art and activity. Finally also Cambden, Hakluyt, [. . .]
            </translation>
        </marginalia>
 
        <underline method="pen" type="straight" language="LA" text="Glareani"/>
        <underline method="pen" type="straight" language="LA" text="annotationes"/>
        <underline method="pen" type="straight" language="LA" text="Chronologia in totam Romanam historiam"/>
        <underline method="pen" type="straight" language="LA" text="Ascensij elenchus ad alphabeti ordinem"/>
        <underline method="pen" type="straight" language="LA" text="Laurentij Vallae"/>
        <underline method="pen" type="straight" language="LA" text="Sabellici"/>
        <underline method="pen" type="straight" language="LA" text="Rhenani"/>
        <underline method="pen" type="straight" language="LA" text="castigationes"/>
        <underline method="pen" type="straight" language="LA" text="diligentia &amp; attentione autores sint lege[n]di"/>
        <underline method="pen" type="straight" language="LA" text="in ipsis Glareani annotationibus"/>
        <underline method="pen" type="straight" language="LA" text="sed utiles &amp; necessarias"/>
        <underline method="pen" type="straight" language="LA" text="futiles autem &amp; nullius pen&egrave; momenti, reiectimus"/>
        <underline method="pen" type="straight" language="LA" text="Velcurionis annotationes eruditae"/>
        <underline method="pen" type="straight" language="LA" text="historia mirific&egrave; illustratur"/>
        <underline method="pen" type="straight" language="LA" text="Heruagios"/>
        
        <symbol name="SS" place="right_margin" language="LA" text="Chronologia in totam Romanam historiam"/>
        <symbol name="SS" place="intext"/>
        
        <mark name="dot" method="pen" place="intext"/> <!-- annotationes, -->
        <mark name="dot" method="pen" place="intext"/> <!-- historiam, -->
        <mark name="vertical_bar" method="pen" place="intext"/>
        <mark name="plus_sign" method="pen" place="intext" language="LA" text="utiles &amp; necessarias"/>
        <mark name="dot" method="pen" place="intext"/> <!-- reiectimus, -->
        <mark name="dash" method="pen" place="right_margin"/> <!-- legen -->
        <mark name="vertical_bar" method="pen" place="intext"/>
        
    </annotation>
</transcription>