<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>

<!DOCTYPE transcription SYSTEM "http://www.livesandletters.ac.uk/schema/aor_20141023.dtd">

<transcription xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
    xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://www.livesandletters.ac.uk/schema/aor_20141118.xsd">
    
    <page filename="00000022.tif" signature="[a8v]" reader="Harvey"  />
    <annotation>
        <marginalia hand="Italian">
            <language ident="LA">
                <position place="full_page" book_orientation="0">
                    <marginalia_text>Semper</marginalia_text>
                </position>
            </language>
            <language ident="EL">
                <position place="full_page" book_orientation="0">
                    <marginalia_text>διότι,</marginalia_text> 
                </position>
            </language>
            <language ident="LA">
                <position place="full_page" book_orientation="0">
                    <marginalia_text>
                        tam politicum, qu&agrave;m militare, curios&egrave; obseruandum: pra[e]sertim in maximis negotiis, atq[ue] 
                        bellis. Neq[ue] enim conducit Effectuum notitia potentissimorum, sine cognitione Causarum. Leguntur Historia[e],
                        vt discatur quod est in actionibus humanis excellentissimum, pace, et bello; domi, et for&igrave;s: discitur, 
                        vt agatur: agitur optim&egrave;, non Effectuum cognitione, magnific&egrave; descripta; sed causarum scientia, 
                        intim&egrave; intellecta. Vnd&egrave; aquilinis h&icirc;c oculis opus: et tam Iudicio solidissimo, qu&agrave;m 
                        Ingenio solertissimo. Cert&egrave; Sine acutissima Analyse, pra[e]sertim politica, et polemica, van&egrave; 
                        leguntur Historia[e], atq[ue] frustr&agrave;. Promptissimum autem, ac pra[e]gnatissimum Romana[e] Historia[e] 
                        prooemium, Eutropij Breuiarium; tam neruosum, atq[ue] efficax, qu&agrave;m succinctum, et pressum. Qua[e] in 
                        Liuio desiderata; &agrave; Sallustio, et Ca[e]sare; &agrave; Paterculo, et Cornelio Tacito supplentur; ea 
                        n&eacute; desiderantur quidem: sed ex illis continu&ograve; supplenda excellentissimis Prudentia[e], 
                        Fortitudinisq[ue] Thesauris. Adde Plutarchum: et ecc&eacute; tam Gra[e]corum, qu&agrave;m Romanorum 
                        preciosissima monumenta: Deus maxime, qu&agrave;m egregia et axiozela? Nihil sagacius, aut profundius: etiam 
                        acria, et valida omnia. Alij etiam insignes, et pra[e]stantes Romani Historici: et in primis Polybius, 
                        Halicarnasseus, Dion, pauci alij de selectiore nota, prudentes, atq[ue] solidi scriptores: sed ista maxim&egrave;
                        necessaria; et publico, priuatoq[ue] vsui vtilissima. Nec ver&ograve; vllo modo pra[e]termittendus Suetonius; 
                        propter arcana principum, et qua[e]dam Rerumpublicaru[m] secreta, dignissimus cognitu; pra[e]sertim Aulicis, 
                        et pragmaticis. Homo liber est, vt Petrus Aretinus, et Machiauellus: nec quicq[uam] celat mysteriorum 
                        Palatinorum, et hypocriticorum. Vtilis est etiam multis egregijs exemplis Valerius Maximus: vtilissimus callidis,
                        solidisq[ue] Stratagematis Frontinus: maxim&egrave;, si illi Egnatius addatur eadem Methodo; huic, Gandinus 
                        Italic&egrave;: quorum sunt eximia pla[e]raq[ue], ac memorabilia Supplementa. Ego Romanis omnibus Historicis 
                        necessari&ograve; addendos censeo; &agrave; Politicis Machiauellum; &agrave; Iurisconsultis etiam Sigonium: et 
                        vtrisq[ue] interdum proderit Bodinus de Rep[ublica] vt bellatoribus egregi&egrave; Vegetius; cum eo, quem dixi, 
                        Frontino, et Polya[e]no. Neq[ue] enim quicq[uam] supr&agrave;, vel Latin&egrave;, vel Gra[e]c&egrave;, vel vlla 
                        Lingua hodierna: seu politic&egrave; quid agendum, seu polemic&egrave;. Interim Liuius maturim&egrave; 
                        perlegendus, et acerrim&egrave;: cuius neminem adhuc noui aut nimis studiosum historicum; aut satis obseruantem 
                        politicum. Ex ijs autem, qua[e] exstant, Liuii explicationibus, nullas malim, qu&agrave;m Velcurionis 
                        annotationes historicas, et politicas: Dana[e]i aphorismos politicos: Machiauelli discursus politicos. Qui et 
                        multos illustrant reconditos locos; et rem ipsam agunt, prudentibus, serijsq[ue] observationib[us]. Nec dubitem 
                        tamen, ex ipsis politicorum principiorum fontibus, altiores adhuc haurire privata[e] industria[e], publicaeq[ue]
                        gubernationis regulas, qu&agrave;m vel ab istis sunt, vel ab alijs obseruatoribus animaduersa[e]. Quomod&ograve;
                        Aurelius Victor refert in Theodosio, Eum Imperatorem aliquando seuera pra[e]cepta habuisse de Liuio. 
                        Vt autem seri&ograve; in Romana historia proficiatur; in primis expedit, tam Eutropij, qu&agrave;m Aurelij 
                        Victoris Breviarium, semper habere promptissimum: et ind&egrave; delectum facere magis exquisitum. Vt 
                        cert&ograve; constabit, personas, res, actiones, omne genus negotia maxim&egrave; excellere. Ea enim Euscopi 
                        tripertita prouincia. Quarta uer&ograve;; uel accurata imitatio, uel strenua a[e]mulatio. 
                        Tandem curios&egrave; contuli Civitatem hominum, cum Ciuitate Dei: et mirific&egrave; placuit collatio, 
                        profuitq[ue] syncrisis, tam politica, qu&agrave;m theologica. Cert&egrave; axiozelus parallelismus.
                    </marginalia_text>
                    <person name="Flavius Eutropius"/>
                    <person name="Livy"/>
                    <person name="Sallust"/>
                    <person name="Julius Caesar"/>
                    <person name="Marcus Velleius Paterculus"/>
                    <person name="Tactitus"/>
                    <person name="Plutarch"/>
                    <person name="Polybius"/>
                    <person name="Dionysius of Halicarnassus"/>
                    <person name="Cassius Dio"/>
                    <person name="Pietro Aretino"/>
                    <person name="Machiavelli"/>
                    <person name="Valerius Maximus"/>
                    <person name="Frontinus"/>
                    <person name="Giovanni Battista Cipelli"/>
                    <person name="Gandinus"/>
                    <person name="Carlo Sigonio"/>
                    <person name="Polyaenus"/>
                    <person name="Jean Bodin"/>
                    <person name="Vegetius"/>
                    <person name="Johannes Velcurio"/>
                    <person name="Lambert Daneau"/>
                    <person name="Aurelius Victor"/>
                    <person name="Theodosius I"/>
                    <person name="Euscopus"/>
                    
                    <book title="Breviarium historiae Romanae"/>
                    <book title="De Republica" />
                    <book title="Politicorum aphorismorum silva"/>
                    <book title="Discourses on Livy" />
                    <book title="Historiae Romanae Breviarium"/>
                    <book title="De Civitate Dei"/>
                </position>
            </language>
            <translation>
                The political and military "reasons why" should always both be carefully studied, especially when dealing with 
                extremely difficult situations and wars. For acquaintaince with powerful results is of no use without 
                understanding of the causes. One reads history in order to learn what is the best in human actions in peace and 
                in war, at home and abroad. One learns in order to act; and one acts best not as the result of understanding 
                the outcomes, however wonderfully they are described, but through an intimate knowledge of the causes. 
                Therefore, here one needs an eagle eye, and both a very solid judgement and an extremely skillful intellect. 
                Really, without sharp analysis, especially political and military, reading historical accounts is vain and 
                pointless. Now the easiest and richest introduction to Roman History is Eutropius’ Breviarium, which is as 
                lively and effective as it is concise and compressed. What is missing in Livy is made good by Sallust and 
                Caesar, by Velleius Paterculus and Tacitus. Indeed, things are missing, but they should be continually 
                supplied from these outstanding storehouses of wisdom and courage. Include Plutarch, and there you have the most 
                valuable monuments of both the Greeks and Romans - by God, how eminent and enviable! There is nothing wiser or 
                more profound; all are penetrating and vigorous. There are also other distinguished and excellent Roman 
                historians, in particular Polybius, Dionysius of Halicarnassus, Cassius Dio and a few others of a more 
                exclusive reputation, judicious and solid authors, but these the most important, and most useful, both in  
                public and private matters. Suetonius also should in no way be overlooked; he very much deserves to be studied,
                especially by courtiers and lawyers, for the secret affairs of emperors, and of states. Man is free, as Pietro 
                Aretino and Macchiavelli say, and nothing hides the secrets of those on the Palatine and the pretenders. Also 
                useful for his many superb examples is Valerius Maximus; extremely useful for his shrewd and powerful 
                stratagems is Frontinus; and especially so if one adds to him Egnatius with the same approach, and to him 
                Gandinus in Italian. They provide many remarkable supplemtary details. I believe that the following authors 
                should absolutely be added to all Roman historians: from the politicians, Macchiavelli; from the legal 
                scholars, also Sigonio; and beneficial for both of these fields from time to time will be Bodin’s 'De 
                Republica', just as Vegetius is extremely beneficial for warriors, and along with him, as I said, 
                Frontinus and Polyaenus. And there is nothing better than these, whether in Latin, Greek or any other modern 
                language, on how one has to act either politically or militarily. Meanwhile, Livy has to be studied as 
                fully and shrewdly as possible. Yet, I know no current historian who studies him very deeply, nor any 
                politician who takes sufficient notice of him. Of the existing commentaries on Livy, however, I like none 
                better than Velcurio’s historical and political notes, Daneau’s political maxims and Machiavelli’s political 
                discourses. These both illuminate many obscure passages, and discuss the subject-matter itself with 
                intelligent and serious remarks. And yet I would not hesitate to derive from these sources of political 
                principals rules regarding private industry and public government that are greater than those noted by 
                these or other observers. As Aurelius Victor reports, the emporor Theodosius from time to time had serious 
                thoughts about Livy.
                But in order to make significant progress in Roman history, it is above all useful always to keep both 
                Eutropius’ and Aurelius Victor’s 'Breviariums' close to hand, and from there to make a more carefully 
                considered choice, so that you can be certain to have the best examples of each kind - with regard to 
                people, subject-matter, and deeds. For that is the threefold province of Euscopus. In fact, there is a fourth:
                either exact imitation, or nimble emulation.
                Finally, I carefully compared the city of men with the City of God. The comparison was wonderfully successful
                and the contrast, both political and theological, very helpful. It was certainly an enviable parallel.
            </translation>
        </marginalia>
    
    </annotation>
</transcription>