<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>

<!DOCTYPE transcription SYSTEM "http://www.livesandletters.ac.uk/schema/aor_20141023.dtd">

<transcription xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
    xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://www.livesandletters.ac.uk/schema/aor_20141118.xsd">
    
    <page filename="00000086.tif" pagination="64" reader="Harvey" />
    <annotation>
       <marginalia hand="Italian">
           <language ident="LA">
               <position place="tail" book_orientation="0">
                   <marginalia_text>Vnd&egrave; multi statim pra[e]clari ciues: vrbs cit&ograve; florens: at Resp[ublica] nimis turbulenta; satis vexata; interdum miser&egrave; afflicta. 
                       Qu&ograve;d si politico illo fundamento nixi, curias, leges, magistratus, mores, ca[e]tera gubernandi vincula, Reip[ublicae] qualitati, statusq[ue] arcanis 
                       conformassent; haud dubi&egrave; mult&ograve; certi&ugrave;s, stabiliusq[ue] rem Romanam tenuissent. Pro qua animaduersione, liberales mihi gratias egit 
                       Philippus Sidneius, insignis Aulicus: ingenueq[ue] fatebatur, se nihil tanti momenti vel in historijs, vel in Politicis legisse. 
                       Videre se passim Romanos, in populari Rep: nimis Senatorios; in Senatoria nimis populares; in regia non satis regios; ciues poti&ugrave;s, qu&agrave;m subditos.
                       Si Reipublica[e] statui fuissent conformes; minim&egrave; se dubitare, quin firmissimam in gentem, populumq[ue] mundi tam foelicissimum euasissent, 
                       qu&agrave;m potentissimum. Qua[e] nostra summa erat horum trium librorum observatio. Nec ego deinceps in reliquis mutaui sententiam.
                   </marginalia_text> <!-- Continued from page 00000085, tail, '...Unde' -->
                   <person name="Philip Sidney"/>
               </position>
           </language>
           <translation>Which from the start made for many excellent citizens, a rapidly blossoming city, but a Republic that was unduly troublesome, 
               rather disturbed and occasionally dreadfully disordered. Yet if they had relied on that political basis and adapted their curias, laws, offices, 
               customs and other bonds of government to the nature of the Republic and the secret principles of the state, they would undoubtedly 
               have held the Roman state much more securely and strongly. And for this consideration Philip Sidney, the prominent courtier, thanked me generously, 
               and he openly acknowledged that he had never read anything of such importance either in historical or political works. 
               That he had observed far and wide Romans who were too much senatorial in a popularist Republic and ones who were too much popularist in a 
               Senatorial Republic, ones who were not royalist enough in a monarchy, citizens rather than subjects. And that he had no doubts whatsoever that if 
               they had adapted themselves to the constitution of the State, that they would have come out as the strongest nation, the most successful and 
               powerful people in the world. And this was our most important observation about these three books. And for the rest I have not changed 
               my opinion since.</translation>
       </marginalia>
        
        <underline method="pen" type="straight" language="LA" text="bouem locuta[m]"/>
        <underline method="pen" type="straight" language="LA" text="anno fides non fuerat"/>
        <underline method="pen" type="straight" language="LA" text="carne pluit"/>
        
        <mark name="dash" method="pen" place="right_margin"/> <!-- futu -->
        <mark name="dash" method="pen" place="right_margin"/> <!-- cru -->
        <mark name="dash" method="pen" place="right_margin"/> <!-- pa -->
        <mark name="dash" method="pen" place="right_margin"/> <!-- prae -->
        <mark name="dash" method="pen" place="right_margin"/> <!-- impe -->
        
    </annotation>
</transcription>
