<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>

<!DOCTYPE transcription SYSTEM "http://www.livesandletters.ac.uk/schema/aor_20141023.dtd">

<transcription xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
    xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://www.livesandletters.ac.uk/schema/aor_20141118.xsd">
    
    <page filename="00000339.tif" pagination="712" reader="Harvey"   signature="dd3[r]"/> <!--wrong page number--> 
    <annotation>
        
        <marginalia hand="Italian">
            <language ident="LA">
                <position place="head" book_orientation="0">
                    <marginalia_text>Maharbalis absolutum consilium, Annibalem reddere potuisset magnum: vt erat Alexander magnus. 
                        Sed minoribus commodis intentus Annibal, maximarum rerum amittit occasionem vnicam. 
                        Vel nunc, vel nunq[uam]. Maharbalis, tanq[uam] Achitophelis peremptorium consilium, instar oraculi. 
                        Pra[e]potentis victoris fuisset pra[e]senti animo, et acerrima alacritate correptum, statim volitasse Romam: 
                        et Vrbem alioqui invictam</marginalia_text>
                    <person name="Maharbal"/>
                    <person name="Hannibal"/>
                    <person name="Alexander the Great"/>
                    <person name="Ahitophel"/>
                    <person name="Julius Caesar"/>
                    <location name="Rome"/>
                </position>
                <position place="right_margin" book_orientation="0">
                    <marginalia_text>, ex improuiso capere attonitam, ac terrore confusam. Cert&egrave; Alexander, et 
                        Ca[e]sar iam iamq[ue] fecissent fulmineo impetu.</marginalia_text>
                </position>
            </language>
            <translation>Maharbal’s bold advice could have made Hannibal great like Alexander was great. 
                Yet as he was focused on smaller benefits, he missed a unique opportunity for really great achievements. 
                It was now or never. Maharbal’s advice, just as the decisive one of Achitophel’s, was equal to an oracle.
                It would have been typical of a superior winner to be won over by his ready mind and really keen eagerness, and hurry immediately to 
                Rome and to take by surprise an otherwise unconquered city, stunned and confused by panic. 
                Alexander first and then Caesar certainly achieved this with an attack with the speed of lightning.
            </translation>
        </marginalia>
        
        <marginalia hand="Italian">
            <language ident="LA">
                <position place="right_margin" book_orientation="0">
                    <marginalia_text>
                        = Occasio in puncto. Aut nunc: aut nunq[uam].
                    </marginalia_text>
                </position>
            </language>
            <translation>Opportunity lies in an instant. It is either now or never.
            </translation>
        </marginalia>
        
        <marginalia hand="Italian">
            <language ident="LA">
                <position place="right_margin" book_orientation="0">
                    <marginalia_text>
                        Miserabile spectaculu[m].
                    </marginalia_text>
                </position>
            </language>
            <translation>A deplorable sight.
            </translation>
        </marginalia>
        
        <marginalia hand="Italian">
            <language ident="LA">
                <position place="tail" book_orientation="0">
                    <marginalia_text>
                        Unic&egrave; expedit ingenti viro, magnarum occasionum momenta instantissim&egrave; arripere stupendo vigore: 
                        et cum interest pra[e]potentem Ducem agere, Hoc agere tremenda vi: nec inausum vllo modo relinquere, 
                        quod conducat maxim&egrave;. Accessorium sequitur principale: et vnum magnum instar mille modicorum. Tunc deficit Annibal, 
                        cum in primis oportuisset excedere: maxim&egrave; in capienda Roma, et defendenda Carthagine. Vbi audebat Animo vincere, 
                        vincebat corpore: vbi vacillabat virtus, ruebat Fortuna. Magna[e] cura[e] magna merces: et contr&agrave;.
                    </marginalia_text>
                    <location name="Rome"/>
                    <location name="Carthage"/>
                </position>
            </language>
            <translation>It is particularly expedient for a great man most insistently to grasp important opportunities with stunning vigor, and, 
                when it is expedient for a powerful leader to act, to do this with tremendous force, and not to leave untried anything whatsoever 
                that may be especially helpful. The accessory follows the principal part and one great result is equal to a thousand mediocre ones. 
                Hannibal faltered at the moment when he should, above all, have proceeded, especially with capturing Rome and defending Carthage. 
                When he mentally dared to win, he won with physically, when valour wavered, Fortune collapsed. The great price of great worries, 
                and the other way around.
            </translation>
        </marginalia>
        
        <underline method="pen" type="straight" language="LA" text="adfafd"/>
        <underline method="pen" type="straight" language="LA" text=""/>
        
        <symbol name="SS" place="right_margin" />
        
        <mark name="dash" method="pen" place="right_margin"/> <!--ui-->
        
        <mark name="plus_sign" method="pen" place="intext"/>
        
    </annotation>
</transcription>

